A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Education Program, Office Files of Frank Bowles FA729
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Education Program, Office Files of Frank Bowles
1962-1968
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA729
2.64 Cubic Feet
The Education Program Papers of Frank Bowles were transferred to the Ford Foundation Archives in 1982. The papers consist of correspondence, inter-office memoranda, and reports. They are divided into two series: Conference Files and Correspondence Files. Arrangement within each series maintains the original order established by Bowles' office. The papers included .3 cubic foot of The Fund for the Advancement of Education material. These files, which Bowles generated during his tenure as President of the Fund, have been incorporated with the TFAE record group.
Conditions Governing Access
Material more than ten years old is open for scholarly research.
Select individual files are restricted, as noted. Permission to access these files must be obtained from the Ford Foundation before scholarly access is permitted.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be restricted from scholarly research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment.
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be restricted from scholarly research at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/RAC Head of Reference.
Separated Materials
Staff and consultant reports and publications have been pulled and accessioned into the Ford Foundation Archives. A cross-reference sheet located within the folders denotes accessioned material. A list of titles removed from the papers is appended to this register. Papers not related to FF activities have been removed.
Biographical / Historical
Frank Bowles, Ford Foundation Program Advisor in the Middle East and Africa office of the International Division, was a member of the Foundation staff from 1963 until 1969. During this period, he held the following positions:
• October 1963, Director, Education Program • January 1967, Advisor to the President, International Education, Office of the President • November 1969, Program Advisor, MEA, International Division
Prior to Bowles' career with the Ford Foundation, he held the following positions:
• 1948-1963, College Entrance Examination Board, Director and President • 1960-1962, UNESCO-IAU, Director, International Study of University Admissions • 1954, University of Puerto Rico, Consultant on the organization of the Graduate School • 1952-1953, TFAE, Director of project studying citizenship education in the Armed Forces • 1947, University of Puerto Rico, Special Assistant to the Chancellor • 1930-1942, 1945-1948, Columbia University, Assistant to the Director; Acting Director; and Director, University Admissions
Frank Bowles was born November 20, 1907. He received his B.A. and M.A. degrees in 1928 and 1930 respectively, from Columbia University. He was awarded ten honorary doctoral degrees.
Mr. Bowles died in 1975.
Scope and Contents
These papers, which consist of six boxes of correspondence, inter-office memoranda, and reports, are concerned with the Education Program for the years 1963 to 1968.
The papers, which are broad in scope, include material related to educational conferences, meetings, or activities attended by Bowles; and correspondence with Foundation colleagues, and individuals in academic, grantee, and other organizations involved in or with FF educational activities.
Mr. Bowles, whose role in the Foundation's Education Program was diverse, is refelected by the papers, accessioned reports, and speeches.
Arrangement
The Education Program Papers of Frank Bowles are divided into two series:
I. Conference Files, 1963-1968 II. Correspondence Files, 1962-1968
Ford Foundation
- Conference Files, 1963-1968; I
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Conference Files (1963-1968), Contains material as it relates to FF sponsored travel Bowles undertook in his capacity as Director of the Education Program and Advisor to the President for International Education.
  Arrangement
  These files are arranged in reverse order of travel taken. Within each folder, the papers are arranged in reverse chronological order.
  - Compton and Merritt Colleges, [Educational Activities], November 1968, 1968 December - October (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Puerto Rico - Establishment of a Center of Experimental Studies for Educational Development, October 6-8, 1968, 1968 December - July (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Beirut and Paris - FF Seminar on University Administration (Beirut), Abidjan Conference (Paris), July 27 - August 8, 1968, 1968 October - July (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Amsterdam - Center for the Study of Education in Changing Societies, July 15-22, 1968, 1967 October - August (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ethiopia - Haile Sellassie I University, April 1968, 1968 March - February (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Villa Serbelloni - Anglo American Conference, March 17-21, 1968, 1968 March - 1967 September (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chicago - Cleveland Conference, November 29 - December 2, 1967, 1967 November - 1965 March (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Vienna - Conference on Ministers of Education of European Member States on Access to Higher Education, November 1967, 1968 January - 1967 March (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Washington, D.C. - American Council on Education, October 11-13, 1967, 1967 October - September (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Williamsburg, Va.- International Conference on the World Crises in Education, October 5-9, 1967, 1968 May - 1967 June (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Montreal - Expo 67, September 1967, 1967 October - September (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Yugoslavia - Yugoslav Elementary and Secondary Schools, June 27- July 5, 1967, 1967 October - January; 1966 June (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Belgium - Ghent Conference, June 5-9, 1967, 1968 October; 1967 October - June (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Ankara, Istanbul, Cairo, Paris, [Educational Activities], May 1967, 1967 August - 1966 November (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Puerto Rico - [Educational Activities], March 13-16, 1967, 1967 March - 1966 November (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Europe - [Educational Activities], February 1-24, 1967, 1967 March - 1966 September (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Netherlands - The University in Developing Nations, December 15-21, 1966, 1967 March - 1964 July (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Paris and London - Organization for Co-operation and Development, December 3-7, 1966, 1966 December - October (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Samoa - [Educational Activities], October 4-12, 1966, 1968 August - 1966 May (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - North Chili, N.Y. - Council for Advancement of Small Colleges, September 1966, 1966 September - August (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Europe - International Institute for Educational Planning, June 5-23, 1966, 1966 July - May (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Magnolia, Ma. - Conference on Innovation in Higher Education, May 19-23, 1966, 1966 May - April (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - California and Oklahoma, May 9-13, 1966, 1966 June - April (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Ethiopia - Haile Sellassie I University, February 19 - March 2, 1966, 1967 September - 1966 January (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Tokyo, Taiwan, New Delhi - [Educational Activities], September 1965, 1966 December - 1965 November (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Tokyo, Taiwan, New Delhi - [Educational Activities], September 1965, 1965 October - 1964 November (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Chile (Postponed), 1965 August - April (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Suffern, N.Y. - Staff Meeting, Motel on the Mountain, August 16-17, 1965, 1965 August (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Mississippi - [Educational Activities], July 25-26, 1965, 1965 October - July (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Cambridge, England - [University Problems], June 27-30, 1965, 1966 November - 1965 January (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - London - Matching Grants to Univsities, February 18-23, 1965, 1965 March - February (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Washington, D.C. - [Educational Activities], January 18-22, 1965, 1965 March - 1964 December (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Trinidad and Jamaica - Conference on Teacher Training, July 20-25, 1964, 1964 August - March (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Aspen, Co. - Humanities Conference, Aspen Institute for Humanistic Studies, May 26-31, 1964, 1964 June - April (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Correspondence Files, 1962-1968; II
  These folders are arranged in alphabetical order. Within those files which are arranged alphabetically by name of organization or subject matter, the correspondence is arranged in reverse chronological order.
  Series II, Correspondence Files (1962-1968), contains correspondence generated by Mr. Bowles during his years at the Foundation.
  - AB-AU, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - BA-BU, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Bundy, McGeorge, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - CA-CU, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Columbia University Seminars, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - COUNSEL, 1968 March - July (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - DA-DY, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - EA-EV, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Eurich, Alvin C., 1965 January - 1968 December (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - FA-FU, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Faust, Clarence, 1964 March - 1967 September (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Ferguson, Alan (Personnel), 1964 March - 1968 July (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - GA-GU, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - HA-HU, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Hayden Spencer (Personnel), 1965 December - 1967 April (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - IN-IR, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - JA-JU, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - KA-KR, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - LA-LO, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - MA-MY, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - NA-NY, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - OK-OW, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - OECD, 1967 January - 1968 May (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - OECD, 1965 June - 1966 December (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - PA-PO, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Pace, Robert, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Quinnipiac College, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - RA-RY, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - SA-SW, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Stinson, Harold (Personnel), 1965 February - 1966 January (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Stone, James (Personnel), 1963 September - 1967 September (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - TA-TR, 1967-1968 (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - UNESCO, 1968 February - December (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - United Nations International School, 1967 December - 1968 November (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - United Nations International School, 1966 October - 1967 December (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - VA, 1968 November - December (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - Von Stoephasius, Renata, 1964 April - 1967 December (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - WA-WR, 1967-1968 (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - YO-ZU, 1968 October - December (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - AD-AT, 1963 December; 1965-1966 (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - Advancement Fellowships (TFAE), 1966 February - September (Box 4, Folder 75)
  - Applicants (TFAE & FF employment), 1966 February - December (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - BA-BU, 1964-1967 (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - Bowles, Frank (DAEDALUS), 1963 December - 1964 January (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - Bowles, Frank (Facilities Loan Fund), 1964 May - June (Box 4, Folder 79)
  - Bowles, Frank (UNESCO), 1963 October - 1965 January (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - Budgets, 1964 April - 1966 September (Box 4, Folder 81)
  - Bundy, McGeorge, 1966 April - December (Box 4, Folder 82)
  - CA-CO, 1963-1966 (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Cameron, Ben, 1963 December - 1965 December (Box 4, Folder 84)
  - Carmichael, Oliver, 1963 December - 1966 October (Box 5, Folder 85)
  - Carnegie Corporation, 1963 November - 1964 January (Box 5, Folder 86)
  - Consultants, 1963 December - 1966 October (Box 5, Folder 87)
  - Council on Foreign Relations, 1965 May - July (Box 5, Folder 88)
  - DA-DU, 1963-1966 (Box 5, Folder 89)
  - Domestic Programs, 1964 October - 1965 June (Box 5, Folder 90)
  - EC-ER, 1963; 1966 (Box 5, Folder 91)
  - Education (Miscellaneous), 1965 November - 1966 September (Box 5, Folder 92)
  - Educational Facilities Lab, 1964 - 1966 February (Box 5, Folder 93)
  - Education and World Affairs, 1965 January - April (Box 5, Folder 94)
  - FA-FU, 1963; 1956-1966 (Box 5, Folder 95)
  - Federal Legislation - Education, 1965 February - 1966 April (Box 5, Folder 96)
  - Fels, William, 1964 December - 1966 June (Box 5, Folder 97)
  - GA-GR, 1964-1966 (Box 5, Folder 98)
  - Graduate Education, 1966 July - September (Box 5, Folder 99)
  - HA-HU, 1964-1966 (Box 5, Folder 100)
  - IN, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 101)
  - Institute of International Education, 1963 November - December (Box 5, Folder 102)
  - International Affairs, 1965 May - 1966 September (Box 5, Folder 103)
  - International Schools Examination Syndicate, 1966 June - December (Box 5, Folder 104)
  - Jencks & Riesman, 1965 April - 1966 July (Box 5, Folder 105)
  - KA-KR, 1964-1966 (Box 5, Folder 106)
  - LA-LY, 1963-1966 (Box 5, Folder 107)
  - MA-MY, 1964-1966 (Box 5, Folder 108)
  - Minority Committee, 1966 July - August (Box 5, Folder 109)
  - NA-NY, 1963-1966 (Box 5, Folder 110)
  - Negro Education, 1964 April - June (Box 6, Folder 111)
  - Nieman Fellows Seminar, 1964 November - 1966 February (Box 6, Folder 112)
  - Office Chrons (Miscellaneous), 1963 November - 1966 October (Box 6, Folder 113)
  - PA-PU, 1964-1966 (Box 6, Folder 114)
  - Personnel, 1964 April - November (Box 6, Folder 115)
  - Personnel, 1963 September - 1964 March (Box 6, Folder 116)
  - Public Affairs, 1965 January - 1966 April (Box 6, Folder 117)
  - Puerto Rico (Miscellaneous), 1964 March - 1965 April (Box 6, Folder 118)
  - RO-RY, 1965-1966 (Box 6, Folder 119)
  - SA-SU, 1964-1966 (Box 6, Folder 120)
  - Saltzman, Henry, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 121)
  - Satellite System, 1966 June - November (Box 6, Folder 122)
  - Southern Association of Colleges and Schools, 1964 August - December (Box 6, Folder 123)
  - TA-TU, 1963-1966 (Box 6, Folder 124)
  - UR, 1966 June (Box 6, Folder 125)
  - VA-VE, 1964, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 126)
  - Vocational Education, 1962 August - 1964 July (Box 6, Folder 127)
  - WA-WY, 1964-1966 (Box 6, Folder 128)
  - Washington, D.C. - Establishment of a National University, 1965 April - 1966 October (Box 6, Folder 129)
  - YE-YO, 1964-1966 (Box 6, Folder 130)
  - ZU, 1963 December - 1964 February (Box 6, Folder 131)
- Appendix A: Frank Bowles Reports Removed
  The following list of unpublished Ford Foundation reports by Frank Bowles were removed from the papers. They are listed in alphabetical order. The number at the left, is the assigned accession number. They have been transferred to the Foundation's Archives collection of staff and consultant reports.
  - American Higher Education in 1990, 1967 (Report 10245)
  - Causes and Effects in Accreditation (Report 10246)
  - The College Admissions Problem in Perspective, n.d. (Report 10247)
  - Conference of Ministers of Education of European Member States on Access to Higher Education. Vienna Conference, 1967 November (Report 10248)
  - Conversations in Europe, 22 June 1964 to July 1964, 1964 July 27 (Report 10249)
  - Democratization. Paper given at the International Conference on the World Crises in Education, Williamsburg, Virginia, October 5-9, 1967, 1967 October (Report 2769)
  - [Educational Opportunities for Negroes], 1966 July 26 (Report 10251)
  - [The Ford Foundation, Education, and Television], 1966 October 31 (Report 10252)
  - Graduate Studies at the University of Wisconsin, 1966 August 12 (Report 10253)
  - Nations With Fully Developed School Systems, n.d. (Report 10271)
  - New Students, New Problems, n.d. (Report 10254)
  - Notes on the Planning of HSIU, n.d. (Report 10255)
  - Patterns of Development in Higher Education. International Review of Education. Vol. XI, n.d. (Report 10256)
  - Planning for Foundation Activities in Europe, 1968 January 5 (Report 10257)
  - Poverty and Education, 1964 June 17 (Report 10258)
  - Present State of Uiversities, 1968 March (Report 10259)
  - Problems of Selection in Developing Societies - An Inquiry, 1968 July (Report 10260)
  - Program Planning Budget - Discussion, 1965 March 26 (Report 10261)
  - Travel Diary: Ankara, Istanbul, Cairo, Paris. May 8-28, 1967, 1967 May (Report 10262)
  - Travel Diary: Ethiopia and Abidjan. April 3-26, 1968, 1968 April (Report 10263)
  - Travel Diary: Europe. February 2-25, 1967, 1967 February (Report 10264)
  - Travel Diary: Europe. April 12-21, 1967, 1967 April (Report 10265)
  - Travel Diary: O.E.C.D., 1967 October 27 - November 25, December 10-18; 1968 January 15-31 (Report 10266)
  - Travel Diary: Yugoslavia, 1967 June 27 - July 5 (Report 10267)
  - Travel Diary for Puerto Rico Trip - March 13-16, 1967, 1967 March (Report 10268)
  - Trip Diary - American Samoa - From October 4, 1966 to October 12, 1966, 1966 October (Report 10269)
  - Visit to Compton College, Los Angeles - Wednesday, November 6, 1968, 1968 November (Report 10270)
- Appendix B: Frank Bowles Speeches Removed
  The following list of Frank Bowles speeches, have been transferred into the FF speech collection. They are listed in reverse chronological order.
  - Talk in Memory of Ned Noyes. Given at the Educational Records Bureau dinner., 1968 October 31 (Report 18655)
  - Speech by Frank Bowles given at Quality Symposium at IIEP in Paris, 1966 Summer (Report 18654)
  - The Dual Purpose Revolution. Given at the National Conference on Higher Education, 1966 March 14 (Report 18653)
  - St. Augustine Commencement Speech, 1966 January 29 (Report 18652)
  - The Shape of Higher Education in 1990. Given at the University of New Hampshire Centennial, 1966 April 12 (Report 18651)
  - White House Conference on International Cooperation. November 28-30, 1965, 1965 November (Report 18650)
  - IAU Meeting, Tokyo, 1965 August 30 (Report 18649)
  - General Education in a Changing World. International Review of Education. Volume XI, 1965 (Report 18647)
  - Educational Opportunity and Political Realities. Academy for Educational Development. Paper No. 2, 1965 (Report 18648)
  - Costa Rica Speech, 1964 May 7 (Report 18646)
  - Bates College Speech, 1963 November 19 (Report 18645)
- Appendix C: Other FF Reports Removed
  The following list of unpublished reports written by other FF staff and consultants were removed from the papers. They are listed alphabetically by author. For each author, the reports are arranged in alphabetical order. The number at the left, is the assigned accession number. They have been transferred to the Foundation's Archives collection of staff and consultant reports.
  - Birnbaum, Norman. The Crises of the European Universities and the Crises of European Culture, 1968 February (Report 10227)
  - Cameron, Ben F. A Five Year Program for the Improvement of Education for Negroes, 1963 December 30 (Report 10228)
  - Feldman, Marvin. Program Possibilities for the Socioeconomical Disadvantaged in Vocational Education for "Blue-Sky" Discussions, 1966 August 4 (Report 10229)
  - Ford Foundation. Civil Rights: The Negro Movement for Equal Opportunity, 1965 March (Report 409)
  - Ford Foundation. Comprehensive School Improvement Program (Report 10230)
  - Ford Foundation. Ford Foundation Grants to Advance Educational Opportunities for Disadvantaged Youth with Particular Emphasis on Negro Youth (Report 1138)
  - Ford Foundation. The Ford Foundation Programs and Developing Federal Activities, 1965 February 23 (Report 2368)
  - Ford Foundation. Grants for Vocational and Technical Education (Report 10231)
  - Ford Foundation. Education Program: Planning Budget Request for Fiscal 1965-1966-1967, 1964 June (Report 10232)
  - Ford Foundation. A Program in Graduate Education, 1966 September (Report 2453)
  - Ford Foundation. Program Planning Budget Report as of March 31, 1966, 1966 March (Report 10233)
  - Ford Foundation. Teacher Education Programs, 1965 September (Report 10234)
  - Griffiths, G.H. Trip to Atlanta and Houston, 1966 March 11 (Report 10235)
  - Harris, Michael. Vocational and Technical Education Program (Report 10236)
  - Meade, Edward, J. Schools, Vocational and Technical Education, and Education Generally, 1963 December 5 (Report 10237)
  - Northrop, E.P. Science in Turkey, 1966 December (Report 3695)
  - Northrop, E.P. A Turkish Effort to Improve Secondary School Mathematics and Science, 1966 November (Report 5940)
  - Saltzman, Henry. [Compensatory Education], n.d. (Report 10238)
  - Stone, James C. Breakthrough in Teacher Education, 1967 January (Report 10239)
  - Stone, James C. The Impact of Forty-Two Ford Foundation Grants in Teacher Education on the Recipients, Neighboring Institutions, School Districts, and State Certification Requirements (Report 10240)
  - Stone, James C. Twenty-nine Million for What?, n.d. (Report 10241)
  - Swearer, Howard. The Foundation and the Foreign Student "Problem" (Report 10242)
  - Von Stoephasius, R. Facilities Loan Fund, 1964 May 19 (Report 10243)
  - Von Stoephasius, R. [The Volkswagen Foundation], 1965 April (Report 10244)
  - Wyzanski, Charles. Notes on a Ford Foundation Trustee's Visit in July and August 1964 to Ethiopia, Kenya, Tanganyika, Uganda, Northern Rhodesia, Southern Rhodesia, and The Sudan, 1964 September 21 (Report 442)